# **Kelvin Wachira**

#### **PROFILE**

With experience working on Palantir Foundry and proficiency in Power BI and SQL, I am able to analyze large sets of data to identify trends and insights that inform product development. I have built dashboards and reports using Power BI and SQL to provide valuable insights to stakeholders and I am a strong communicator able to present findings and recommendations to cross-functional teams.

#### **PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE**

Data Engineer02/2021 – presentMoringa ☑Remote

 Achieved a 25% improvement in data accuracy, as measured by a reduction in errors, by implementing new data quality control processes.

- Developed and maintained dashboards that led to increase in stakeholder engagement, as measured by an increase in dashboard usage, by developing and maintaining dashboards that provided valuable insights.
- Achieved a 50% reduction in data processing time measured by the elapsed time to complete tasks by automating data-related tasks using Python scripts and SQL.
- Accomplished significant time and resource savings as measured by the time and effort
  required to run the data pipeline before and after automation by implementing automation
  and optimization techniques to improve the efficiency of the data pipeline.
- Realized a 15% increase in team productivity, as measured by the number of tasks completed quarterly, by training and mentoring junior team members on data analysis techniques and tools.

Data Analyst
O1/2020 - 05/2021
ALU School of Business
Remote

- Created and ran market-wide surveys, compiled data from previous studies and surveys, and composed comparative reports. This provided insights during the review of the M.B.A. program, such as current hiring trends as well as on-demand courses.
- Provided comprehensive analysis, which informed prioritization of best practices for career development initiatives of the school's graduate students.
- Analyzed key performance indicators regarding program development student and faculty performance. This included designing dashboards and reports and coordinating and facilitating various lectures.
- Facilitated Coaching sessions and workshops for 30+ alumni to understand their postgraduate journey and help them map and develop their personal and professional journeys.

# Software Engineering.

Hence ♂

- Performed data cleaning and standardization using Python on the company's database, reducing data validation on the APIs and reducing API latency by 5% while increasing Data Integrity and Visibility.
- Led the 2-month software development of a Chromium-based React extension, enabling users to give and receive meeting micro-feedback on video conferencing tools such as Google Meet.
- Collaborated with a team of 5 developers to migrate the team's partial codebase, hosted on Palantir Foundry, from Django-based logic to vanilla python logic.
- Implemented in-house python libraries for consistency and ease of accessibility of core functions used by the team on Palantir Foundry.

Tools used: Javascript | Reactjs | Postgresql | Foundry | Python | Django | REST API | Linux

#### **Software Engineer Intern**

African Leadership University. 🛭

• Demonstrated accuracy, thoroughness, and orderliness by Performing quality control on students' grades and facilitating accurate feedback loops from faculty to students.

Remote, Rwanda

Kigali, Rwanda

- Used Data Studio and JavaScript to create a grades delivery system that reduced lecturers' grades upload time by 20% while allowing students to view, filter, and compare individual scores to class/peer-group average scores on dashboard visualizations.
- Automated 35 % of first-year leadership certification feedback systems by restructuring the feedback pipeline using JavaScript on google scripts.

Tools used: Javascript | REST API | Google Data Studio | App Scripts

## **Projects Manager Intern.**

Moringa School

05/2019 – 12/2020 Nairobi, Kenya

- Created and maintained custom data trackers for teams by automating data collection, cleaning, and sorting processes using Python, which improved the processing time of new students by 30%.
- Spearheaded research and created a document management system that facilitates easy
  communication between the admissions and marketing teams and easy tracking of
  documents while preparing the admissions team for scale-up by implementing a new
  document management system framework.
- Deployed new in-house reporting templates for teams, ensuring consistency in the format in which data was collected, maintained, and stored.
- Analyzed past scholar internship-related data, drew insights, and provided recommendations to improve the graduate experience and address pain points.

#### **PROJECTS**

## **Machine Learning**

Leveraged **Data Mining** and **Machine Learning** to Predict if a moringa school boot-camps applicant will succeed and what traits strongly influence final results. This involved training models on cleaned applicants' data using the **RandomForestClassifier**, **AdaBoostClassifier**, and **XgBoost models**. The trained models then informed whether new applicants would succeed in the program.

#### **ORGANIZATIONS**

#### African Leadership University.

Teaching Assistant.

- Collaborated closely with professors to prepare data-driven reporting to evaluate students' performance and provide recommendations by assessing students' assignments on the Learning Management System.
- Provided comprehensive academic support and tutorials in both one-to-one and in-class settings to arouse the enthusiasm of students to participate in course discussions. This resulted in an increase of 12% in the class average.
- Analyzed students' grade records, identified the trends and areas that need to improve, and created an excel dashboard template for future analysis.

#### African Leadership University.

Student Leader.

• Formed the first student leaders' council body on campus, which foresaw the implementation and improvement of communication and feedback from the students to the facilitators/lecturers, executives, and vice versa.

#### **EDUCATION**

#### **Bsc Hons In Computer Science.**

African Leadership University □

**Relevant Coursework:** Data Mining, Machine Learning, Artificial Inteligence Data Structures & Algorithms; Data & Decisions; Databases; Cloud Computing; Web Development; Computer Networks; Software Engineering; Systems Programming; Discrete Mathematics; Data Mining; Machine Learning.

**G.P.A.:** 4.1

## **SKILLS**

# **Programming**

Python; Django; JavaScript; NodeJs; ExpressJs; ReactJs; Dart; Ruby on Rails; Git. Data Structures and Algorithms; Postgresql; MongoDB, C.

# **Data Management and Analysis.**

Cloud Foundry; Google Data Studio; Salesforce; SQL; SOQL; Excel; Python; Pandas.